<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The plot discovered and counterplotted commended in a letter to a private friend, / from a true-hearted well-wisher to great Britains happinesse.</title>
            <author>True-hearted well-wisher to Great Brittanes happinesse.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90788</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2593</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E171_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E171_26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16974</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860128</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860128</idno>
            <idno type="VID">157052</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90788)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 157052)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 30:E171[25], 30:E171[26])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The plot discovered and counterplotted commended in a letter to a private friend, / from a true-hearted well-wisher to great Britains happinesse.</title>
                  <author>True-hearted well-wisher to Great Brittanes happinesse.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Vnderhill, and are to be sold at the Bible in Wood-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1641]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a preliminary blank leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>A letter to a private friend -- The covnterplot -- Articles concerning the ministers of England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:157052:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:157052:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PLOT DISCOVERED AND <hi>COUNTER PLOTTED</hi> Commended in a Letter to a private Friend, from a true-hearted well-wiſher to great <hi>Britains</hi> happineſſe.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. <hi>124.1.-6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If it had not beene the Lord who was on our ſide, may <hi>Iſraell</hi> now ſay.</p>
               <p>If it had not beene the Lord who was on our ſide when men roſe up againſt us.</p>
               <p>Then they had ſwallowed us up quick when their wrath was kindled againſt us.</p>
               <p>Then the waters had overwhelmed us, the streame had gone over our ſoule, then the proud waters had gon over our ſoule.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed be the Lord who hath not given us a prey unto their teeth.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Vnderhill,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Wood-ſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:157052:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:157052:2"/>
            <head>A Letter to a private Freind.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hiles I looke on the Ladie of <hi>Iſlands,</hi> I meane great <hi>Britaine,</hi> and ſee her clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with the mourning weed of ſo many ſad, ſtrange, and diſhonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble accidents which have fallen out in theſe latter times, mine eyes run wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and my head is a Fountain of teares. So that one while the unhappie occurrences of State doe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:157052:3"/> make me deſire a ſequeſtred and contemplative life, that I may with freedome bewaile the ſinne and diſhonour of our Nation; another while I ſeem tranſported with zeal for God his Church, and glory of our Nation; preſſed in ſpirit with renewed thoughts of indignation againſt the inſtruments of this preſent diſtraction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> In my retiredneſſe, mee thinkes I have diſcovered the plot of <hi>Britains</hi> ruine (as you may perceive by the inſuing diſcourſe) together with the contrivers of it and their principles.</p>
            <p>Afterwards I ſhall propound unto you the way for the Counterplot, which may be wel contrived in theſe times, ſuiting that high and honourable Court of Parliment, whoſe wiſdome is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able to diſcover the ill intentions of enemies to Church and State, and provide meanes of preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſeaſonably.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> When I looke on that illuſtrious Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, I conſider it as a well conſtituted bodie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving right ſymetrie in all parts, the humours well tempred, ſo that there is no feare of any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsive predominancie of one above an other; their ſenſes internall and externall active, fancie nimble, intellect profound and ſerious, memory ſtrong and retentive, beſides their hearing, ſeeing, taſting, ſmelling, and feeling very good and quick; ſo that it ſeemes preſumption for one that moves in the inferiour orbes to preſent objects to ſuch accurate and high intelligences; Yet Sir, whiles paſsion, judgement, ſenſe of mine own inſufficiencie, together with loyalty to my God,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:157052:3"/> King, and Countrey, ſtruggle thus in the wombe of my conceptions, I am at a ſtand, and almoſt reſolving to daſh my thoughts in the ſhel, and cruſh them in their <hi>embrio,</hi> but at laſt conſidering theſe preſent Halcyon dayes, wherein the Kings-fiſher begins to make his neſt upon the waters, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but promiſe my ſelfe ſerenitie in bringing forth my conceptions, eſpecially having ſo fair op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to put them to nurſe, and education in your boſome, whoſe wiſdome, learning, tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and particular faithfulnes, I value as ſufficient obligations of truſt and confidence.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe Sir, it is not mine intentions, ſo to confine my conceit unto your private acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and tuition, but if it find favour in your eyes you may preſent it to the view of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Edward Dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Walter Earle,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>William Bruerton,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Nathaniell Barnardiſton,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Pim,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hambden,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. John,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Purphry,</hi> or others of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons houſe, whoſe names are precious with mee, and their minds ſo ſtored with the grounds of all true nobility, that I doubt not but they will know how to give a favourable acceptance, or elſe to pardon the errours of well intended fancie.</p>
            <p>In the mean time I commit the tuition and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of my conceptions to your ſelfe, if you ſee cauſe, to ſtrike them <hi>in cunabulis</hi> afore they bee preſented to any further view, yet be pleaſed to give them a burial, beſeeming ſuch as are diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of one of your faithful friends, of Chriſtian and true Engliſh parentage.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:157052:4"/>
            <p>In my diſcourſe I ſhall deſcribe, firſt the Plot, ſecondly the Counterplot; in the Plot I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the Plot it ſelfe, the Contrivers, the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
            <p>Firſt for the Plot it is <hi>Mahomets,</hi> the introduction of a new forme of government; wherein <hi>Mahomet</hi> borrowed <hi>à Judais, à Gentibus, à Chriſtianis,</hi> from the Jew, from the Gentile, from the Chriſtian, ſo our laſt yeeres have borrowed in their imaginarie forme from three ſeverall Places, <hi>Sodome, Egypt, Babylon:</hi> From <hi>Sodome,</hi> pride, idleneſſe, fulneſſe of bread, inordinate luſts, intemperance, &amp;c. From <hi>Egypt,</hi> cruelty, oppreſſion, tyrannie over Gods Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell, and ruling in Church and State without any rule, but will, like <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in <hi>Egypt.</hi> From <hi>Babylon</hi> the Marchandize of Gold, Silver, precious ſtones, and Pearles, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.12. beſides theſe, Beaſts, Sheepe, Horſes, Charriotts, ſlaves, and ſoules of men <hi>vers</hi> 13. without queſtion Sir, <hi>Sodome, Egypt, Babylon,</hi> or <hi>Rome,</hi> were the preſidents or coppies of our latter times, according to which they have drawn upon our State, to the life, the Atheiſme of <hi>Sodome,</hi> the tyranny of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the idolatry of <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Babylon.</hi> A moſt helliſh device to ſqueeſe the Juice of three ſuch vicious governments into this of ours, which before the late times of degeneration was the fame and glory of the whole World. The truth of this will appeare by the voluminous Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the grieved partie, before the high and honourable court of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Contrivers of the plot, whom I
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:157052:4"/> ſhall referre to theſe ſeven heads. Firſt the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Miniſter; Secondly the corrupt Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; Thirdly the innovating Prelate with his officer; Fourthly the profeſſed Papiſt; Fifthly the Popiſh Proteſtant; Sixthly the rigid Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian; Seventhly the Libertine.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the ſcandalous Miniſter, I meane ſuch as preach very ſeldome, and then very coldly, happily farr above the capacitie of the hearer, or if hee preach often, his preaching and practice croſſe the one the other, hee preacheth againſt ſwearing, and yet is a common ſwearer himſelfe, againſt drunkenneſſe, and yet is a common drunkard himſelfe, at leaſtwiſe a common bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, an intimate friend and ordinary acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the common Toſpots, making the Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop the chiefe place of Studie and contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; accounting thoſe the fineſt fancies which are begot over a ſparkling cup, and thoſe divine raptures which are occaſioned by exhalations drawne from the good Ale and Sack; my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is not <hi>Sir,</hi> to wound any moderate man, who upon juſt occaſion of buſineſſe may looke into a Tavern, or ſometimes to expreſſe humanity or courteſie to a friend may ſometimes take or give a cup of wine, provided it be inoffenſively car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, in reguard of time, perſons, or companie, place, moderation, and the like. Such only I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend <hi>Sir,</hi> who delight more in chirping compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie in the Ale-houſe or Tavern, then they doe in Communion with the Saints, or their Wives and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:157052:5"/> Families at home; that account their own hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes priſons, and taverns paradices, whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults in this kind, ſuch Miniſters own wives, and Tavern Boyes are beſt able to diſcover.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe ſuch alſo I reckon amongſt ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Miniſters as doe fill their Neighbours eares, and eys, with obſcaen &amp; wanton words and carriages, making laſcivious ribaldry the fitteſt muſique at a table-meeting, <hi>Tom Trinkilo</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more acted to the life, then by many of theſe, who go under the name of the Angells of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and by their mimicall, apiſh, and ridiculous cariages, ſeek to pleaſe the humour of the brave ſparks and gallants of our times.</p>
            <p>Laſtlie ſuch alſo are ſcandalous miniſters as are carried with bitter and malicious ſpirits, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtrict and more exact practiſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which can ſcarcely forbeare to diſgorge their foule ſtomacks in the pulpit againſt them who walke cloſer with God then themſelves, which can finde more Rhetorike to advance ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie then ſubſtance, which can finde no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie in a man that practiſes in all the maine points of Religion, if tender in conſcience about a ceremony, but copious and full in teſtimony of a good fellow, a boone companion, a common ſwearer, if zealous only in matter of ceremony, ſuch as cannot ſuffer a pious conſcientious man to paſſe without a jeere, nay haply perſecute him, out of his pariſh, if he conform not in folio to all indifferent ceremonies, ſuch bitter ſpirits as theſe give great offence, whiles they arrogate the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:157052:5"/> names of Chriſts Miniſters, and Ambaſſadors, and in their lives ſhew neither humility, nor ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall charitie and love of their Maſter: Theſe and ſuch like are they which pull downe more by their practice then they build up by preaching. Theſe are the watchmen on the wall which meeting with the Spouſe of Chriſt pluck her vaile from her, wound &amp; buffet her, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.7.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the corrupt Magiſtrate, ſuch I meane as buy, and therefore muſt ſell Juſtice, which makes the face of his prince, not the laws, the rules of Juſtice, which in a tryall conſider more the perſon then the cauſe, ſuch as delays or haſtens an hearing according to his ſatisfaction of the ſenſe of feeling, ſuch as wry Juſtice upon a great mans letter, or private information that the perſon before him is a Puritan, as if he that were a Devill ſhould not have his due.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, innovating Prelates with their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, whether Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Deans, Archdeacons, Commiſſaries, Officialls, &amp;c. ſuch are they which manage juriſdiction Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, whether Excommunications, Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, Synods, Corrections, and other Courts, <hi>ad collectionem nummorum non ad correctione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> morum.</hi> They rather viſite mens purſes then their perſons, ſpinning their Cannons and Articles like the Spider his web, where little flies are caught but great ones breake through, theſe are ſuch as have learned in theſe latter times, the art of commutation, they had rather have a hundred commutations then one publique ſatisfaction
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:157052:6"/> and acknowledgment. They will connive, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, and what not, ſo that they may have Dr. <hi>Argent</hi> to make the motion; Lords, Knights, Gentlemen and others, may whore, bee drunk, and what not, ſo that the fat of their ſins may come <hi>ad culinam Epiſcopi,</hi> to the Biſhop and their Officers Kitchin. Such I ſuppoſe are our corrupt Prelates as know how only (if they preach at all) to ſpeake <hi>placentia,</hi> to ſow pillowes under the arme-holes of Prince and People, ſuch as uſe Rhetorike to ſcrew Prerogative as high as Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and conclude as much to belong to the King in way of command as to God Almighty.</p>
            <p>But, O wonder of ages, I meane our gratious King, whom God hath preſerved ſo, that hee hath no more beene poyſoned with Epiſcopall flatterie.</p>
            <p>Examine all ages, was there ever preſident for ſo many ſuſpenſions in theſe Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as by our late Biſhops? was there ever ſuch a fire kindled as in theſe our days by Prelates, to the hazard of three Kingdomes at once? were there ever Prelates and their officers ſo groſſe for notorious luſts, for oppreſsion, extortion, raſing fees, picking advantages, preaching ſeldome or never? Were there ever any Biſhops ſince the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, and the reformation in thoſe days, that have brought us ſo far back to a violent neceſsity of ſuch uſages as might more neerely conforme us to the Romiſh Religion and Ceremonies, bowings, ducking, cringings, Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:157052:6"/> &amp;c. Theſe <hi>Sir</hi> and ſuch like are they who have improved all opportunities and diligence to diſcourage and ſupplant all Schollers in the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities, and Miniſters in their ſeverall Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, who have been orthodox and induſtrious, Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Proteſtants, if moderate about the ceremonies, and have planted right men (as they call them) in the roome of Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox and Pious men, haply learned, but ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Simonicall, ſcandalous, and inclining to all Romiſh corruption, whereunto their Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Patrons, I mean the Biſhops, have invited them, either by their precepts or examples. Theſe <hi>Sir</hi> and the like are thoſe who are the innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Prelates, and have <hi>quantum in illis</hi> brought ruine upon Church and State, and laid the Plot for an univerſall alteration of both.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The profeſſed Papiſt, I mean ſuch whether convict or not convict as acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg the Popes ſupremacie, never come to our Churches, admire their Popiſh prieſts, eſpecially their Jeſuites (thoſe infernall Locuſts which have come out of the bottomeleſſe pit) as their holy fathers, ſuch as account Proteſtants Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, and it a ſacred point of devotion to kill Proteſtant Princes, though in a barbarous, baſe, and trecherous way, ſuch as ſerve God by Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and account ignorance the mother of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, coſtly, unneceſſary, and uncommanded ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies the glory of the Church. Theſe are they who are fallen into the great conſpiracie
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:157052:7"/> againſt great BRITAINES proſperitie.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, The Popiſh Proteſtants, I mean ſuch as are exceſſively charitable concerning the profeſſed Papiſt, they love not to come to Church oftener then the lawes enforce, if the State will give them leave they will conforme to any Popiſh uſage, and are indeed Papiſts in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very point but Supremacie, and preſts mariages, and in theſe likewiſe in their judgments they are very favourable to the Romiſh way.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The rigid Arminian, who accounts no Doctrine ſublime but what advances his own opinion about predeſtination, free-will, falling from grace, and the like.</p>
            <p>Theſe account all men unſound, not rightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, or very dunces, that are not of their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, theſe finde no muſique in a Sermon, where the Miniſter gives not a touch upon the Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſtring.</p>
            <p>Theſe pretend the advancing of good life by their doctrine, while in the mene time if you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them generally, there are none more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, proud, vaine, and ſcurrilous, then they that prate moſt in the Arminian cauſe.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, the Libertine, ſuch I underſtand to be the ſwearer, drunkard, whore-maſter, profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Sabbath, ſcorner &amp; deſpiſer of others, following no calling but their ſinful luſts, harſh &amp; cruell in their dealings, as though God had gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them a charter to doe what they liſt, for theſe and the like doth the land morne, many are the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:157052:7"/> Princes thereof, and a fruitfull land doth God make barren, for the ſin of the inhabitants that dwell therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I can never looke on theſe ſeven ſorts of men, but I call to mind that <hi>Septemfluus Amnis</hi> the River <hi>Nilus</hi> which ſwel'd and overflowed all EGYPT.</p>
            <p>Yet if it pleaſe his Majeſtie, and this high and honorable Court of Parliament, that three ſorts of the ſeven, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſcandalous Miniſter, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novating Prelate with his Officer, together with the rigid Arminian be well diſciplined, you ſhall obſerve the other foure, the corrupt Magiſtrate, the profeſſed Papiſt, the popiſh Proteſtant, and the Libertine preſently brought in by the power of the Goſpel, and if it pleaſe his Majeſty with the Parlament to plant in the rooms of the ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dalous Miniſters and Arminians, approved miniſters for doctrine and life, it would be a true piece of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie beyond the Biſhop-craft practiſed in theſe later times for the advancing of their Hierarchie.</p>
            <p>And if it ſo pleaſe the wiſdome of the State to beſtow the Lands and Impropriations belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to the Biſhops and great Churches (beſides what ſhall be thought fit to ſettle on the Crown) upon Miniſters conſcientious, induſtrious, able, and learned, where meanes is moſt wanting, to make ſome proviſion for Miniſters widdowes and children, as they doe in the French Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, to maintain Schollers in the Univerſitie, and enlarge Schoole-maſters allowance, I dare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:157052:8"/> undertake, that learning would not bee diſcouraged, but the preſent generation would pray, and poſterity for ever would riſe up to praiſe God for ſuch a bleſſed King and ſuch a happie Parliament.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, <hi>Sir,</hi> Three diſcouragements whiſper in my eares, all pretending that this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration is not ſafe nor fecible.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>1</label> Firſt, if Eccleſiaſtical government be altered, why may not the civil alſo be deſired to be alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon the ſame terms? <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, there is more general grief, and deſire of alteration in the Eccleſiaſtical government then in the Civil. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the conſcience is more concerned in the one then in the other, the purſe is pinched in the one, the conſcience in the other; examine this wel you ſhall find ſomething worth notice. Thirdly, the Scripture ſeemes to preſcribe more for Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall government then Civill, leaving all Nations to libertie for their ſeverall lawes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided none croſſe his own eternall commands.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> Secondly doth not reaſon require a levell in the Commonwealth as wel as a parity in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall dignities? <hi>Anſ.</hi> I am confident no moderate wiſe man would deſire ſuch a levell as to have all Eccleſiaſticall grounds ly in a flat, high Mountaines are fitter for barren <hi>Wales,</hi> then fruitfull <hi>England,</hi> little hils doe not diſparage the moſt fruitfull grounds. If ſome Miniſter have one, ſome two, ſome three hundred pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> haply more, ſuch hills will not bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:157052:8"/> of, only let the Mountains be throwne into the Seas, I meane the greater promotions, then ſhall the little hils skip like lambs, when the World is more equally divided one graine of faith may remove theſe Mountaines into the middeſt of the Sea.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>2</label> Secondly the Church may bee called the younger ſiſter of the common-wealth, there was a Common-wealth in <hi>Iſrael</hi> before the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of <hi>Levie,</hi> Commonwealths were before Apoſtles, Paſtors, or Teachers, ſeniority uſually gives dignitie, though <hi>Rachell</hi> the younger ſiſter was faire and more admired by <hi>Jacob,</hi> yet <hi>Leah</hi> the elder ſiſter was preferred, for it was the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Countrey (ſaid <hi>Laban.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Thirdly much advantage may come by level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Church, but unconceiveable miſchief by levelling the Common-wealth, ſandie Hills may be eaſily levelled, high ſtonie Rocks can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without difficultie. <hi>Verbum ſapienti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>3</label> Thirdly the King will not eaſily conſent? <hi>Anſ. Sir,</hi> I fear it not, never was better King upon the Throne then our gratious Soveraigne, never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more deepely engaged to maintain Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, but I am confident that God who hath given him a gratious heart, will give him a diſcerning ſpirit, to ſee the evil conſequences of degenerate Epiſcopacie by the cleere information of his great Counſell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> excuſe me for that my <hi>Remora</hi> hath ſtayed my ſhip a little longer among the projectors then
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:157052:9"/> I did intend, I will now come to the principles by which they have wrought.</p>
            <p>Firſt no ceremony no Biſhop, no Biſhop no King, a principle it is true, which (it may bee) pleaſed the palate of a wiſe man, but as it hath beene uſed and applyed it hath opened a gap to deſtruction, ſchiſme, ruine, and danger.</p>
            <p>It hath beene uſed as though a King could not rule without the help of a Biſhop, whereas Kings ſwayed their ſcepters before the Epiſcopal digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie was ever knowne in the World, and as like themſelves as ever ſince, and as though a Biſhop could not ſubſiſt without a ceremonie, whereas the Biſhops of the Apoſtles and primitive times (as they were then called) had few or no ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies at all. The further you come from Chriſt, the Apoſtles, and primitive times, the more ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies you ſhall finde, in <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time there were but few in compariſon of after times, yet he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of a Judaiſme, and multitude of ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, above that which is meet, that in a few hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeers were crept into the Church.</p>
            <p>I conceive the Apoſtles and primitive Biſhops were more pious, more conſcientious, more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious, and did more good, in feeding and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning the Church of God then our late Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and yet they uſed few or no ceremonies in compariſon. <hi>Sir,</hi> theſe <hi>Septemvirated</hi> conſpirators if you obſerve, have all admired this principle, witneſſe their inordinate zeal for the ceremonies as though there were no Religion but in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:157052:9"/> practice of theſe; have not the laws of God, I meane the expreſſe morall Commandements, beene ſlighted and neglected, the breaches of it eaſily diſpenced withall? The fundamentall lawes of the Kingdome ſhaken, while theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly projectors have advanced their Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Canons? for my part I have ever tooke a King for a beame of the Deity caſt into an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle of the Earth, and that Judgment and Juſtice make the throne ſtable, ruling according to Law is the greateſt honour and ſafety of a Prince, and therefore God requires by <hi>Moſes,</hi> that the King ſhall read in the book of the Law night and day; there are two ſorts of Lawes, Gods owne Laws, and the fundamentall lawes of a Kingdome or State, the King is to ſee the execution of both theſe, and it is moſt ſafe to preſerve them with all tenderneſſe, ſo that if a King have a care of theſe, he may bee ſufficiently ſupported without the help either of Biſhop or Ceremonie; methinks it is a diſparagement to the Crowne to bee ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by Biſhops; ſure I am <hi>Solomons</hi> throne was ſupported by Lyons; and for Ceremony to ſupport Biſhops, It ſeemes ſuch a ſandy foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, that with a violent ſtorme the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be waſhed away, and the whole building may eaſily fall. Goe through all the ſeven ſorts of men whom I have charged for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators of State, you ſhall hardly finde a man but working a great deale of trouble, by vertue of this principle; I will cloſe all with croſſing and thwarting of the proverb, A King may be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:157052:10"/> without a Biſhop, and an Apoſtles Biſhop with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Ceremony.</p>
            <p>The ſecond principle, that a papiſt is much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſter then a puritan, and much more to bee fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured; a damnable principle according to the intention and application of it, and of the effects that have followed in this Kingdome. No queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Machiavil, Ignatius,</hi> or the Devill began to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply this old Hereticall name in ſuch an extended and generall way. For in theſe latter times every man that ſubſcribed unto the Doctrine of the Church, if he was tender in matter of ceremonie hath beene reputed a Puritan, nay, every man that will not ſweare, be drunk, wanton, ſcoffe and jeere others, he is a puritan, though conformable to the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſo that the late projectours have united together in this principle and by it have much advanced their deſignes: upon this ground, the Papiſt hath beene cheriſhed as the honeſter man, men of moſt refined life, and exact godlineſſe and have ſhewed forth eminent vertue in practice, have beene brow-beaten, diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced, and perſecuted, drunkards have beene the good Sonnes of the Church, temperate men the ſtubborne children of their mother; <hi>O Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, O Mores,</hi> what ſtrange times were we fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, when light was called darkneſſe, and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe light, ſweete ſower, and ſowre ſweet, good evill, and evill good, when the wicked ſhall bee juſtified for a reward, and the righteouſneſſe of the righteous ſhall bee taken away from them? This
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:157052:10"/> principle hath beene followed with ſuch helliſh zeal that Religion and Vertue are almoſt bereft of life and ſenſe, for this principle hath put out the eyes, cut off the legges and hands of Religion and Vertue, Help Lord for faith and truth are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt periſhed, and diſcouraged for looking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſonnes of men.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, libertie is ſweet, a principle which is acknowledged moſt true, provided it be not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in longitude and latitude above the true naturall dimenſions of it; If it had beene ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no further then Gods ſervice it had beene perfect freedome, but let it be onely underſtood of the ſatisfaction of the carnall will and ſenſuall appetite then liberty is dangerous, and of bad conſequence. Now <hi>Sir,</hi> ſurvey ſeriouſly the latter times, you ſhall obſerve the ſcandalous Miniſter, the corrupt Magiſtrate, the innovating Prelate and his Officers, the profeſſed Papiſt, the Popiſh Proteſtant, the rigid Arminian, and the Libertine, all ſayling in one and the ſame channell of carnal libertie, and crying out, <hi>Te, te, nos poſcimus omnes,</hi> all of them with one conſent deſire libertie, not freedom of conſcience in indifferent &amp; undeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined things, for this you ſhall ſcarce have one hand amongſt them, but libertie to ſin, to have their luſts, their heterodox and unſound opinions, libertie to caſt off the bonds of truth. This princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple doth cement their affections one to an other, and unite them more ſtrongly againſt all divine obedience, and hath hetherto made the late con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies againſt Church and State more formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:157052:11"/> and dreadfull. Theſe and the like diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call principles our late projectors have manna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with what faithfulneſſe they can, againſt the God of order, the law of charitie, the rules of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, ſo that the beautie of theſe glorious Iſlands by theſe and the like deviſes is much defaced and obſcured. <hi>Sir,</hi> having thus ſurveyed theſe Proje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and their principles, methinks it ſeemes our dutie, and the dutie of all good Chriſtians and true <hi>Engliſh</hi> hearts, to Petition unto the high and honourable Court of Parliament againſt theſe, as underminers of State happineſſe, either for their reformation, or elſe puniſhing or diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing of them; for ſo long as theſe have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique encouragement in our State, neither can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be ſecured, nor the throne and tranquility of the Kingdome well eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>Its true, whiles we looke upon the numbers of theſe confederates, upon their ſtrength (for they look like the ſons of <hi>Anak</hi>) or upon their union, for they ſeem like the ſcales of a Whale which a ſword cannot pierce and divide eaſily, they render themſelves to our eyes like the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abites</hi> and <hi>Amonites</hi> to <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> in a very terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble forme, and for our parts wee ſeeme a little flock of ſheepe, and like graſſehoppers in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon: Yet mee thinks (under correction of your better judgement, unto whom I render my ſelfe as a learner) there is hope in <hi>Iſrael</hi> concerning this thing provided the countermine be wel wrought and managed, I ſhall therefore crave your aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to make up by your mature thoughts
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:157052:11"/> what is wanting in my conceit of a Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plot.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>THE <hi>COVNTERPLOT.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</hi> there is no better Counterplot to the workers of iniquity then for the oppoſite ſide to worke contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, to countermine errors with truth, unrighteouſneſſe with righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, uncharitableneſſe with charitie, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence with moderation, and all ſinne with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere practice of pietie. This for a generall will hold as the great mine which the Church of God is to raiſe againſt the enemies of it.</p>
            <p>But beſides this there are three particular mines which I conceive are moſt fitting at this preſent, to raiſe againſt the aforenamed confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate projectors againſt great <hi>Britain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt a well managed Commiſsion, the ſecond is a well conſtituted and orderd Church-aſſembly, the third is a right frame of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall government. Firſt a well managed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, I underſtand by that, firſt Commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:157052:12"/> choſen by the houſe of Commons, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Houſe of Lords, which ſhall bee no parties nor delinquents as far as can bee diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, theſe choſen out of every Shire or Dioces. If the Shire be barren of able and ſufficient men, then to appoint ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers rather then delinquents, and thoſe qualified with integritie, wiſdome and reſolution.</p>
            <p>Secondly when the Commiſsioners are thus choſen for both the houſes, to move his Majeſty for ſufficient authority for the managing of the ſaid commiſsion. That the Commiſsioners may bee enabled to give oaths, to call before them any parties offending or others for witneſſes as they ſhall ſee cauſe, and to have as large power to puniſh contempts, non aparences, or abuſe of the Commiſsioners, as the Archbiſhops Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors were wont to have, in their Metropoliticall viſitations.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, when the Commiſsioners are thus choſen and armed with authority, then to have a booke of Articles according to the tenour of what I ſhall propound in the latter end of the diſcourſe, and the ſaid Commiſsioners to have power to admoniſh, to enjoine recantation, and to deprive Miniſters, or elſe to return their names into the Houſe of Commons to bee cenſured there, and haply it might conduce well to the worke, to have a Regiſter allowed to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners for every Shire or Dioceſſe, and ſome ſmall fee to be paid to the ſaid Commiſsioners
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:157052:12"/> towards the charges of the ſaid Commiſsioners and Regiſter, by every delinquent, as in like caſes hath beene allowed in Biſhops viſitations.</p>
            <p>Secondly a well conſtituted aſſembly or Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, I meane an aſſembly of godly, orthodox, learned, wiſe, and well tempered Divines, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by the ſingular prudence and providence eſpecially of the Houſe of Commons, which haply might be done moſt opportunely, when the commiſsion hath firſt diſcovered the innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Prelates, the ſcandalous Miniſter, Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Popiſh Proteſtants within theſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and diſabled them from judging, adviſing, or determining in any Church affaires till their reformation be eminent and well noted in the World.</p>
            <p>In an aſſembly or Synod thus conſtituted, me thinkes <hi>Sir</hi> it would doe well to have the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church well determined and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planed, ſo that in matter of Doctrine wee might conſent with all Proteſtant Churches, and (if it were poſsible) that an agreement might bee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured for betwixt us and the Southern and Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Churches, and al Churches to be accounted Chriſtian, which ſhall be found to agree in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Doctrine; who knowes but the ſingular induſtry and wiſdome of ſuch a well conſtituted aſſembly, may fetch in the <hi>Aſian, African, Euro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pean,</hi> and <hi>American</hi> Churches into greater unitie and brotherly correſpondencie, and haply to the incredible ſtrength of the Chriſtian party againſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:157052:13"/> all the ſworne enemies of Chriſt Jeſus, Nay, who can tell but that ſuch a reconciliation wrought in matter of doctrine may be a ſpeciall meanes to undermine the walls of <hi>Babylon,</hi> to bring under the <hi>Mahumetan,</hi> and to render the Lord Chriſt as a more acceptable <hi>Meſsias,</hi> to his old and forſaken people the <hi>Jews.</hi> But now, <hi>Sir,</hi> I cannot but pauſe, being tranſported with ſuch high thoughts, and deſignes; but are not wee the tools and inſtruments to ſerve divine providence? Doth not Creation, Redemption, &amp; the conſtant benignitie of Gods providence en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage us to ſerve God in his higheſt and greateſt ends? Is there any part of the World where God hath ground better furniſhed with men of parts, Learning, Tongues, Arts, Sciences, brave and Noble Reſolutions, Ancient, and Renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Valour, and Honourable Atchievements, then in theſe <hi>Britiſh</hi> Iſles? Hath God ſo honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and qualified Great <hi>Britain,</hi> with ſuch ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie and eminencie in all things? And ſhall not Great <hi>Britain</hi> reach out its Vertues to ſerve her Lord and Maſter in his greateſt and higheſt Deſignes? Well, <hi>Sir,</hi> Let us not bee diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, let us do, <hi>quantum in nobis,</hi> for our God hath often honoured himſelfe by the weakeſt Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I deſire the old boundaries and meeres, between actions neceſſary, and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, may be ſearched out, well viewed, reſtored, and determined; the loſſe of Meere ſtones often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:157052:13"/> occaſioneth quarrels betwixt neereſt Neighbours, and deareſt Friends, for many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres by-paſt, the Meer-ſtones betwixt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and indifferency have beene (for the moſt part) loſt and buried under ground, ſo that neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity hath encroached upon indifferencie, or indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferencie upon neceſſitie.</p>
            <p>Heavens help us in this, for in earth wee could never find, for many hundred yeers, men of ſuch moderate and temperate ſpirits as would allow neceſſitie and indifferencie their owne, without wrong to the one ſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I profeſſe, I would not have God to loſe one foot of his own ground, nor the Conſcience its Chriſtian privilege, neither yet the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the leaſt due that God allows him; only I could wiſh it well determined in a competent and impartiall Church Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>Firſt, whether the Conſcience be tyed to obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in any thing, but what God requires in his Word, by way of precept, or naturall and neceſſary inference, and whether it be fit to ſtrain an inference too far and too curiouſly?</p>
            <p>Secondly, whether all things be not indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, wherein the Scripture hath not determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the Conſcience free to uſe them or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, whether the libertie of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in indifferent things was not purchaſed by Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If it be the Churches priviledge
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:157052:14"/> what man, or civill Magiſtrate, hath power to take away my priviledge by Chriſt, without my own conſent, teſtified by my ſelfe, or others tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in my behalfe?</p>
            <p>Fifthly, whether a Nationall Synod (after the Church is well purged) be not a fit way to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude our libertie in indifferent actions, eſpecially there being ſome to repreſent the people (haply a Committee of the Houſe of Commons, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in the Worke) for the finding out of the bounds of indifferent actions, and the preſcribing Laws concerning them?</p>
            <p>Sixthly, whether any ſuch aſſembly may make any Law for indifferent actions, but with a Proteſtation of Revocation upon inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces obſerved, and generall ſcandals?</p>
            <p>Seventhly, whether charitie be not as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary together with other generall Rules, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. and as order or ſubjection to Magiſtracie, and how theſe can be all managed without croſſing, or violence to ſome ſide?</p>
            <p>But now (mee thinks) whiles I looke into the Arke, I cannot but tremble and cry out with the Apoſtle, <hi>O the depth;</hi> theſe are <hi>arcana Eccleſiae,</hi> or fitter for a well conſtituted Synod, then for any particular, or private perſon to ſearch into them, neither are they fit to be diſcuſſed in ſuch a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod without ſingular moderation, charitie, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, profound judgement, and integritie.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>Sir,</hi> I have done with my ſecond Myne, which being well wrought, will blow
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:157052:14"/> up many of the above-named Conſpirators. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Sir,</hi> Let us encourage the work to the utmoſt for the reconciliation of all Chriſtians in matter of doctrine, who knows but that God, Great <hi>Britains</hi> Lord, will account the <hi>Indies</hi> too mean a recompence for her faithfulneſſe in erecting the Kingdome of Chriſt through the World, and making the light of the Goſpel more glorious? Sure I am, the opportunitie for the Weſt <hi>Indies</hi> is fairer then ever, for my part I dare undertake to cleere it, and for neerer Kingdomes, who knows but they may ſay to us, as thoſe in the Prophecie of <hi>Zacharie, Wee will goe with you, for God is with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, A good frame of Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which may repreſent the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> comming downe from Heaven, wherein the Lambe may bee the light, and that unerring Truth of Gods Word the only Rule whereby to work this frame of building.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I am confident, wee ſhall never be free from ſcandalous Miniſters, <hi>Arminians,</hi> Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and Popiſh Proteſtants, till a new frame of Government be determined, which may more certainly finde out, diſcover, and ſuppreſſe the Enemies of God and his Church, then this of ours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> my meaning is not to aſsigne any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar forme or way for Church-government, that is fitter for a Nationall Synod, then my ſelf, only into your boſome I dare vent my conceit in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:157052:15"/> ſome generals; I wiſh the three ſeverall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be well ſurveyed, the Epiſcopall, the Presbyteriall, and the Independent ways in <hi>New England,</hi> to refine them all in a Church Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, And wherein all or any of them may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme us, more neerly to the Word, and ſute with the diſpoſition and neceſsitie of our church, ſo much, <hi>Sir,</hi> deſire we may follow in any one or all of them, but where theſe ſeverall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or any of them, do croſſe the Word, and are inconſiſtent with the preſent and diſtracted condition of our Church, I humbly pray to God Almighty, they may be reprobate, ſo that Chriſt only may rule in his Church, according to his commiſsion from his Father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I believe you will find upon the examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the three ſeverall Governments, ſome thing worthy of admiration, and imitation, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of them; None of the three Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments but may have their ſeverall defects or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities, one out of all would doe well, yet ſo as nothing be taken but what agrees with the Word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> by this time, I am afraid I have ſpent your patience, but if you pleaſe well to conſider the premiſes, you ſhall haply finde ſome Gold, though much droſſe; ſome ſparks of Vertue, and ſuch notions as being caſt abroad, in the World, may beget ſome Noble and brave thoughts in the minds of our Nation; though I give but hints, profound heads can make larger
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:157052:15"/> commentaries, your judgment I know is able to fan away the chaff, and to keep the pure grain to your ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> It were damnable preſumption in mee to thinke the Parliament ſhould be bound to my directions, <hi>per omnia,</hi> yet if ſuch or the like ways were held, I doubt not, but Great <hi>Britain</hi> would be the wonder of Ages, and a great contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the greater light and glory of all <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Churches in the World; who knows, but God hath humbled us in the eyes of the World, to raiſe us to higher honour, and that the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne</hi> glory, I mean the <hi>Scots,</hi> and wee ſhould be neere a breach, to make way for a ſtronger, and neerer Union? bones broken and well ſet are ſtronger afterwards, ſo the <hi>Scots</hi> and we with our brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> may with more conſtant, and cordiall Union, advance the glory of our God, our King, and Countrey, to make their names famous amongſt <hi>Chriſtians, Jewes,</hi> and <hi>Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans;</hi> the bloud of <hi>Richard</hi> the Firſt, and <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt, is not wholly loſt amongſt us, neither of our Progenitours, whoſe names were terrible as far as the <hi>Holy Land;</hi> the neer Union lately made with the brave, ingenious, and warlike <hi>Hollander,</hi> I looke on as the firſt-fruits of a greater U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and a Reconciliation in Doctrine and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions amongſt <hi>Chriſtians</hi> through the whole World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I know you are active, Let us ſtir and ſet forward Gods great works in the World; who
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:157052:16"/> knows what God would have done? haply in the midſt of theſe great deſignes, the diſtreſſed <hi>Palſgrave</hi> unto whom our Nation owes much for neerneſſe in bloud, may be relieved: miſtake me not, let all be deliberately ſurveyed, my end is not <hi>movere quieta, ſed quietare motum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> wee are all Gods tools to work with all, let him be the end of all, wee may wiſh and will, but the Kingdome, power, and glory is Gods, let him have the honour unto all Eternitie. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
